<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-css/driver.css" type="text/css"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
JS-XMLRPC User manual
$Id: xmlrpc_js.xml,v 1.10 2008/03/07 16:53:57 ggiunta Exp $
-->
<book lang="en">
  <title>JS-XMLRPC</title>

  <subtitle>version 0.4</subtitle>

  <bookinfo>
    <date>XX YYYY 2007</date>

    <author>
      <surname>Gaetano Giunta</surname>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2007 G. Giunta</year>
    </copyright>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This collection of Javascript classes provides a framework for
    writing XML-RPC and JSON-RPC clients.</para>

    <para>Main goals of the project are ease of use, flexibility and
    completeness. And of course, full API compatibility with the <ulink
    url="http://phpxmlrpc.sourceforge.net/">PHP-XMLRPC</ulink> library.</para>

    <para>XML-RPC is a format devised by <ulink
    url="http://www.userland.com/">Userland Software</ulink> for achieving
    remote procedure call via XML using HTTP as the transport. XML-RPC has its
    own web site, <ulink
    url="http://www.xmlrpc.com/">www.xmlrpc.com.</ulink></para>

    <para><ulink url="???">JSON</ulink> is a format devised to ease
    serialization and deserialization of common data types without incurring
    the overhead that is normally associated with XML. It is a subset of the
    Javascript language, and as such it is easily manipulated within web
    browsers.</para>

    <para><ulink url="http://www.jsonrpc.org">JSON-RPC</ulink> is a remote
    procedure call protocol that uses HTTP for transport and a json syntax
    extremely similar to the xml-rpc one.</para>

    <para>Many thanks to the original author of the PHP-XMLRPC library: Edd
    Dumbill of <ulink url="http://usefulinc.com/">Useful Information
    Company</ulink>, to Jan-Klaas Kollhof for the Jsolait library and to the
    Yahoo! YUI team, for building such an incredible toolkit.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>What's new</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>version 0.4</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>added method setUserCredentials to xmlrpc_client, as the
            'parent' php lib does in its latest version</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>added support for the &lt;ex:nil/&gt; tag from the apache
            library, both in input and output (output regulated by the
            xmlrpc_null_apache_encoding variable, input by
            thexmlrpc_null_extension one)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>base64_decode now trims whitespace</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>updated bundled yui to version 2.5.0</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>fixed a bug in error log handler when using
            firefox+firebug</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>fixed a bug in xmlrpc_decode with structs</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>fixed a bug in parsing cookie headers in http
            responses</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>allow lib to work in Windows Scripting Host
            environments</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>added two demo files, for WSH and VB</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>version 0.3</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A lot of bugs have been fixed in all areas of encoding and
            decoding xmlrpc values</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The debug and error logging mechanism has been rewritten,
            and will take advantage of Firebug when detected</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>There is better support for Firefox when setting debug mode
            to clients, and for Safari when the port is not specified in the
            server url</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The function <function>wrap_xmlrpc_server</function> (from
            the original PHP api) has been implemented, and a couple of bugs
            fixed in <function>wrap_xmlrpc_method</function></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>version 0.2</title>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><methodname>client.send()</methodname> supports async calls.
            In order to activate this functionality, pass a function as third
            parameter. Note that the timeout parameter only has effect in
            async calls.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the <function>wrap_xmlrpc_method</function>() function is
            finally working. It makes the wrapping of remote webservicesinto
            native javascript functions (a.k.a. proxying) a snap</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>the debugger can nowgenerate example code for invocation of
            remote methods</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>minor assorted bugfixes, especially for Internet
            Explorer</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>a minified (ie. compact) version of the library has been
            included in the distribution. It can be used instead of the
            standard version on webservers where bandwidth savings are
            important</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>better documentation has been included in the distribution,
            most notably the (almost complete) API specification</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>version 0.1</title>

      <para>Initial release of the library. Many "nice bits" are still missing
      (see <link linkend="Chapter5">Chapter 5</link> below), but the basic
      encoding/decoding functionality should be ok.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>System requirements</title>

    <para>The library has been tested on Internet Explorer versions 6 and 7,
    Firefox 2.0 and Opera 9 and Safari 3 beta, plus Windows Script Host
    5.6.</para>

    <para>Your mileage may vary on other browsers / javascript hosts.</para>

    <para>The XMLHttpRequest object is used by the client component to send
    http requests to servers, so it is definitely a must-have.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Files in the distribution</title>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>lib/xmlrpc_lib.js</filename>: the XML_RPC classes.
          This is the core library needed by all other files</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>lib/jsonrpc_lib.js</filename>: the JSON-RPC classes.
          Include this to enable suppor for JSON-RPC</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>lib/xmlrpc_wrappers.js</filename>: helper functions
          to "automagically" convert calls to remote webservices into
          javascript classes / functions</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>lib/jsxmlrpc-min.js</filename>: this file contains
          the 3 files lisetd above, stripped of all comments, whitespace and
          indentation and glued together. It is provided as a commodity for
          deployment on webserver setups where download bandwidth and latency
          are important</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>debugger/debugger.html</filename>: a graphical
          webservice debugger</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>debugger/visualeditor.html</filename>,
          <filename>debugger/visualeditor.css</filename>,
          <filename>debugger/xmlrpc_display.js</filename>,
          <filename>debugger/xmlrpc_tree.css</filename>, plus all the other
          files (taken from the YUI distribution): visual editor component for
          creating arbitrarily nested xml-rpc/json-rpc values. It can be used
          as part of the js-xmlrpc debugger, as well as in the debugger that
          comes with the PHP-XMLRPC library or the docxmlrpcserver class part
          of PHP-XMLRPC EXTRAS</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>doc/xmlrpc_js.xml</filename>: the docbook source
          file for this manual</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>doc/*.html</filename>,
          <filename>doc/*.css</filename>: this manual, in HTML format</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>README</filename>; <filename>NEWS</filename>,
          <filename>Changelog.txt</filename>: as the name implies, useful
          information bits</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>Makefile</filename>,
          <filename>doc/makefile</filename>: make scripts used to package the
          library for distribution, and optionally, to install the packaged
          version on target servers</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title id="Chapter5">Known bugs and limitations</title>

    <para>WARNING: the code used to parse json-rpc messages is based on usage
    the <function>eval()</function> javascript function, and does virtually no
    type checking. As such it is extremely prone to javascript code injection,
    and should only be used to communicate with webservices you absolutely
    trust.</para>

    <para>Missing functionality that is part of the PHP-XMLRPC library
    include: handling of charset encoding (where explicitly requested by the
    user); timeout in send() methods for the sync calls; compression of
    requests; handling of compression, chunked encoding in
    parseResponseHeaders (the response body is decoded correctly by the
    browser); encoding/decoding of anonymous js classes via an xml attribute
    (since it is hard to recover a class name, we could encode instead all
    methods as code); allow username/password auth be specified in URL when
    creating a client object; using client credentials for https auth</para>

    <para>Other: demo cases, reduce JSLint warnings, a testsuite and speed
    tests</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Support</title>

    <para>JS-XMLRPC for PHP is offered "as-is" without any warranty or
    commitment to support. However, informal advice and help is available via
    the JS-XMLRPC website and the PHP-XMLRPC mailing list.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis>JS-XMLRPC</emphasis> development is hosted on
        <ulink
        url="http://phpxmlrpc.sourceforge.net/jsxmlrpc/">phpxmlrpc.sourceforge.net/jsxmlrpc</ulink>.
        Bugs, feature requests and patches can be posted to the <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/phpxmlrpc">project's
        website</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <emphasis>PHP XML-RPC interest mailing list</emphasis> is
        run by the author. More details <ulink
        url="http://lists.gnomehack.com/mailman/listinfo/phpxmlrpc">can be
        found here</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>For more general XML-RPC questions, there is a Yahoo! Groups
        <ulink url="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/xml-rpc/">XML-RPC mailing
        list</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <ulink
        url="http://www.xmlrpc.com/discuss">XML-RPC.com</ulink> discussion
        group is a useful place to get help with using XML-RPC. This group is
        also gatewayed into the Yahoo! Groups mailing list.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>On Yahoo! Groups you can find a mailing list dedicated to <ulink
        url="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/json/">JSON</ulink>, and one
        to <ulink
        url="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/json-rpc/">JSON-RPC</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Class documentation</title>

    <para>Where's the meat?</para>

    <para>Unfortunately, the documentation of the API exposed by the library
    has not (yet) really been integrated into the manual.</para>

    <para>Luckily, it is available in HTML format as part of the distribution:
    just look for the <ulink url="???">doc/api</ulink> directory.</para>

    <para>For more details, the manual that comes with the php-xmlrpc library
    might prove helpful: after all the two libraries share the exact same API
    (except for a handful of small quirks due to differences in the underlying
    language, detailed in Apendix A). It is available online at <ulink
    url="http://phpxmlrpc.sourceforge.net/doc-2/">http://phpxmlrpc.sourceforge.net/doc-2/</ulink></para>
  </chapter>

  <appendix>
    <title>Known differences from the PHP-XMLRPC API</title>

    <para>Although the library is designed to implent the same programming
    interfaces of the php-xmlrpc library, differences in the languages
    (javascript vs. pgp) and underlying platform (browser vs. php engine)
    prevent a complete a match. This list details the known differences in the
    behaviour of the two libraries. Please note that most of the discrepancies
    deal with private members of objects, unusual usage patterns and little
    known coner cases, and are mostly of interest to people that wish to
    extend / modify the library rather than just use it.</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>the internal, private structure of the xmlrpcval objects is
          slightly different</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>xmlrpcresp.serialize() produces a complete xml chunk,
          including the xml prologue. In php-xmlrpc the prologue is
          omitted</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>adding data to a struct value using the same keys of elements
          that already exist in the struct might produce different
          results</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>xmlrpcresp objects have no private member
          'content-type'</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the values of the global object 'xmlrpcTypes' (an array in
          php) differ (although the keys are the same)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the method <methodname>xmlrpcval::addScalar()</methodname>
          does not coerce values to the appropriate type when declaring them
          as boolean</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the method <methodname>xmlrpcmsg::parseResponse()</methodname>
          can take a string as second parameter (which is assumed to be the
          full http response headers text)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>all classes have an <methodname>init()</methodname>
          constructor method (used for subclassing)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>when using a browser as javascript host, the client object by
          default inherits the browser settings with regard to http
          connections, eg. it can have keepalive ON, make use of HTTP 1.1 and
          will support receiving compresssed content and content in many
          charsets (the browser taking care of the transcoding)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the client object by default will send to the server any
          cookie received in previous requests. In php-xmlrpc all cookie
          handling has to be done by hand</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>the client object does not support setting ssl certificates,
          proxies, ntlm authorization</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>all output generated by the lib is performed by two functions:
          <function>xmlrpc_error_log</function> and
          <function>xmlrpc_debug_log</function> (for which the user can set up
          a message handler), whereas in php it is sent to stdout and
          stderr</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>method names are case sensitive in javascript, and this lib
          respects camelCase convention</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </appendix>
</book>
